<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse of the turkes lawe called Alcaron. And also it speketh of Machamet the nygromancer</title>
            <title>Koran.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1519</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120689</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855883</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855883</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21391</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04940)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21391)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 70:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse of the turkes lawe called Alcaron. And also it speketh of Machamet the nygromancer</title>
                  <title>Koran.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In fletestrete in the sygne of the Sonne by me Wynkyn de worde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1519?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon. Conjectured publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mu.hammad, --  Prophet, d. 632.</term>
               <term>Koran --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21391:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21391:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth a lytell treatyſe of the turkes lawe called Alcaron. And alſo it ſpeketh of Machamet the Nygromancer.</head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>a clergyman preaches to nuns from a pulpit</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:21391:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>two wealthy men, one accompanied by the devil, and one by an angel, talk to each other from balconies while a woman begs on the ground below</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:21391:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to knowe and to here ſome newe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges for to refreſſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wyttes and vnderſtandynge. So wyll I ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what wryte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> turkes lawes / whiche lawe in many poyntes accordeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lawe &amp; is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of Machomet / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in his lawe vſed a worde (oteidite. That is to ſaye kylle. So all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll not byleue in theyr lawe they flee them. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of oure lorde Iheſu cryſt / for he byddeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall loue them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue not vs and praye for oure enemys. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> turkes ben charged to theyr byleue. But the cryſten people be not ſoo / but amyably lerned &amp; teched. And whan y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the predycante or prechour ſhal go to preche theyr fals byleue he hath a naked ſwerde in his hande as longe as his ſermon ſhall endure &amp; laſt. Or elles he putteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſwerde in a hyghe place wher as euery body may beholde it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is there for to fere and threten them therwithall. And we cryſten people putteth a crucyfyxe in the myddes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche on hyghe for humylyte &amp; not for fere or threte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge lyke as the turkes do the forſayd ſwerde. And ſo forthe I wyll procede and wryte of theyr lawes and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the whiche is named comenly Alcaron. And ſome men dothe call it the boke of Meſaap and ſome of them be of dyuers langages and in lyke wyſe of dyuers cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche boke Machamet made and gaue it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. In the whiche boke this fals nygromancer Machamet wrote amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge other thynges as many one hathe redde and ſene here before that they the whiche ben good ſhall go vnto paradyſe and they the whiche ben euyll to helle / and that byleueth all the ſaraſyns / <pb facs="tcp:21391:3"/>¶ And yf a man aſketh theym what paradyſe meneth they ſaye it is a place of delyte and Ioye / where a man ſhall fynde all maner of delytes and fruytes / &amp; all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of fruytes at all tymes / and the ryuer renneth myl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / wyne / hony
/ and freſſhe water. And they ſhall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue fayre houſes / after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue deſerued them here and thoſe ſame houſes ben made of precyous ſtones / of golde and ſyluer / and eche man ſhall haue ten wyues / &amp; all maydens / and alſo they ſpeke &amp; troweth vpon the vyrgyn Mary and in lyke wyſe vpon the Incarnacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our lorde Iheſu cryſt. ¶ And how that Marye was lerned of the aungell and that gabryell ſayde vnto her that ſhe was cho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en before all other women from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge of the worlde / and that wytneſſeth theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that tolde of her and of the Incarnacyon of our lorde Iheſu cryſt. And that ſhe conceyued and bare a chylde and yet ſhe was a mayden. And they ſaye that our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Iheſu cryſt ſpake as ſoone as he was borne / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was very god &amp; prophete in worde and dede &amp; that he was meke / &amp; ryghtwys vnto euery body withoute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ony vyce. ¶ And they ſaye alſo that whan the aungell tolde her of the Incarnacyon ſhe hadde greete drede / for ſhe was but yonge and there was one in that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree the whiche hadde the crafte of ſorcery &amp; nygroma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye and men called hym Takney the whiche with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tement coude make hymſelfe lyke vnto an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell And he wente often and layde by maydens and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was our lady aferde of hym for ſhe wende that the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell hadde ben Takney that wente to the maydens And ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iured hym and badde hym tell yf that he we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Takney. And the aungell badde her not drede for he was very aungell &amp; meſſager of our lorde Iheſu cryſt. <pb facs="tcp:21391:3"/>And alſo thyr boke ſayth that ſhe hadde chylde vnder palme and than ſhe ſhamed and wepte &amp; ſaye that ſhe wolde haue ben deed / and the chylde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted her and ſayd. Ne time as maria. That is for to ſaye drede the not Marye. And in many other places the boke ſayth that he ſpake as ſoone as he was borne. And they ſaye alſo that he was ſente from oure lorde almythy for to gyue example vnto all theym that were in the worlde at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme and that ſholde come after and that god ſhall deme all good vnto heuen and all euyll vnto helle there for to abyde in payne euerlaſtynge. And that our lorde Iheſu cryſt is the beſt prophete nexte vnto god / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was a very prophete
/ &amp; gaue the ſyghte vnto the blynde men / and he let the lepres / and reyſed the dede &amp; ſtyed a quycke vp in to heuen. And yf that they may fynde a boke of the goſpelles and manely of the goſpell of Miſſus eſt angelus gabriel. They do grete worſhyp therto. And alſo they faſt ſeuen monethes in the yere / and they ete not but vpon the nyghtes / and thenne they kepe them from theyr wyues / and whan they be ſyke they be not conſtreyned vnto that faſt. And the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſpeketh of the Iwes &amp; ſayeth that they ben wycked people for they byleue not that Iheſucryſt is one with god and they ſaye that the Iewes lyeth vpon our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and on her ſone Iheſucryſt for they ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dyd hym not vpon the croſſe. And the ſaraſyns byleueth ſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oche in our fayth that they ben lyghtely conuerted whan men dothe preche vnto them the fayth of our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de Iheſu cryſt. And they ſaye that they knowe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr lawe of Machamet ſhall fayle as dothe the lawe of the Iwes and that the cryſten lawe ſhall laſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:21391:4"/>worldes ende. And yf a man aſke theym wherin they byleue they ſaye in god almyghty maker of heuen and erthe and all other thynges that ben therin and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute hym is nothynge done nor bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and at the day of dome all thynge ſhall be rewarded after theyr deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge and all thynge is true that cryſt ſayd by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes of the ꝓphetes. And alſo Machamet bade in his Alcaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that euery man ſholde haue two or thre wyues and nowe they take ten or twelue or as many lemma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as they may gete. And yfony of theyr wyues dothe a myſſe to theyr huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des they maye dryue them away and take another but he muſte gyue her a parte of his goodes. Alſo whan men ſpeketh of the fader and ſone and holy ghoſt they ſaye that they are thre perſones &amp; not one god but they ſcorne it and ſpeke not therof but of the trynyte. But they ſaye that god ſpake or elles he was domme and god is a gooſt or he were on lyue and ſaye that goddes haue grete ſtrength and ſo ſaye they in ſcorne. And the ſaye alſo that Abraham and Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met were well in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god for they ſpake w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym dyuers tymes. And they ſaye in lyke wyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met was the very meſſanger of god and they haue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny good artycles of oure fayth and they all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptures &amp; the prophecyes for they haue theym wryten in the goſpelles and in the byble in theyr la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and ſo they knowe moche of the holy ſcrypture but they vnderſtande it not but after the lettre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell and therfore ſaynt poule ſayth thus.</p>
            <q>¶Littera occidit. <pb facs="tcp:21391:4"/> ſpiritus viuificat.</q>
            <p>¶ That is to ſaye the lettre ſleeth and the ghoſt quyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth. And the ſaraſyns ſaye that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iwes kepe not the lawe that Moyſes toke vnto them. And alſo cryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men do not well bycauſe that they kepte not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ten com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes of the goſpell the whiche Iheſu cryſt gaue vnto them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therfore I ſhall tell you what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoudan ſayde vnto a cryſten man vpon a daye in his chambre. He made for to auoyde out of his chambre lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des &amp; ladyes and all that was therin for he wolde ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with hym in counſayll. And whan all was auoyded he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cryſten men gouerned them and he ſayd ryght well bleſſyd be god. And the ſoudan ſayd ſykerly naye for he ſayd that our preſtes ſayd not theyr ſeruyce as they ſholde doo nor gyue not good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of good lyuynge vnto the people as they ought for to do. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ſholde go for to ſerue god they go vnto the tauerne and lyeth there i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glotonye all the daye and all the nyghte and eteth and drynketh as beeſtes and wote not whan they haue ynoughe and he ſayd that cryſten men enforced them for to fyght togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and echone to begyle other / and they be ſoo proude that they wote not how for to clothe them nor how lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge nor howe ſhorte now ſtreyte now wyde in all maner of guyſes / and ſayd that they ſholde be meke &amp; ſymple and ſoth faſt &amp; do almeſſe as cryſt dyde in whome they byleue. And they be ſo couetous that for a lytell ſyluer they ſell theyr trouhte and theyr chyldren &amp; theyr ſyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; theyr wyues that one taketh another mannes wyfe and fewe holdeth theyr trouthe. And therfore he ſayd for theſe ſynnes cryſten men haue loſt all the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:21391:5"/>that we holde. For thoughe ſynne hathe god put this lande in to oure handes and not thrugh ſtrengthe but thorughe your ſynnes and wretchedenes.</p>
            <p>¶ But we knowe ryght well for a certay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te that whan ye ſerue well your god that he wyll helpe &amp; ſocoure you In ſuche wyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man can withſtande agaynſt you. And that alſo we knowe well by oure prophecyes that the cryſten men ſhall wyune theſe landes agayne wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſerue theyr god well. But whyles that they lyue ſo ſynfully &amp; ſo wretchedly as they do we haue no drede of them. And thenne he aſked the ſoudan how that he knewe ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the eſtate of cryſtendome. And the ſoudan ſayd that he knowe it bothe of lordes and comons / and by his meſſangets the whiche he ſente thorughte all countrees as they were marchauntes with perles &amp; precyous ſtones and dyuers other marchaundyſes for to knowe the maner of all countrees. And then the ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dan called in the lordes agayne. And thenne he ſhewed vnto me the greteſt lordes of that contree / the whiche dyde ſpeke you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>yght well euer ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e and the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan alſo and than I had grete mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayll of the dyſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre of our fayth. And ſo the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>kes and ſaraſyns y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſholde be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orned to Iheſu cryſte by good example / they ben drawen awaye thorughe our ſynne and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge for they ſaye ſot he / wherfore it is grete py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te for to beholde and here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynnes that reygneth now thorughe all cryſtendome. But the ſaraſyns ben true For they kepe well the lawe or wrytynge of Alcaron y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſaye that god ſente then by his meſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger Macha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>met vnto whome they ſaye that Saynt gabryell ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke often with hym / &amp; tolde to hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of oure lorde / <pb facs="tcp:21391:5"/>And this Machamet was borne in Arabye / &amp; he was fyrſte a knaue and kepte the horſes in the ſtable and he wente after marchantes So he came ones in to Egyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te with a marchaunt, And egypte was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme cryſten and there was a chapell beſyde Arabye / wherin dyde dwelle an hermyte &amp; whan he entred in to the chapell the whiche was but a lytell hous and a lowe anone it ganne for to waxe as grete as a palays gate. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſyns ſayd that it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte myracle that Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met dyde in his yongthe. And afterwarde Machamet beganne for to be ryght wyfe. And he was afterwarde a grete aſtronomyer &amp; ſyth he was keper of all the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the prynces of Corydan and he gouerned and kep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te it full wyſely. And whan that the prynce of Corydan was deed he wedded his wyfe the lady that men called Quadryge. And this fals Machamet fell often into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fallynge euyll / wherfore the lady was wrothe bycauſe that ſhe hadde taken hym to her huſbande. But this Machamet made her to byleue that at euery tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he fell ſoo that the aungell gabryell ſpake vnto hym
/ &amp; that for the grete bryghtneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aungell he felle dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. This machamet regned in Arabye the yere of our lorde Iheſu cryſt. vi. ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth and twenty. And was of the kynred of Iſmael that was Abrahams ſone &amp; he begate hym on Arage his chambere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaraſyns ben calld Iſmahelytes and ſome Agaren / &amp; ſome of Agar. And ſome there be that ben called Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytes / and ſome Amonytys after the two ſones of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. And this fals Machamet loued well an holy man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche dwelled in a wylderneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was a myle from the mounte of Synay in the vale as men dothe go fro Arabye vnto Caldas / &amp; it is but a dayes Iourneye fro <pb facs="tcp:21391:6"/>the ſee whan marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes come from Venis. Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met went often i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to that hermytage wherfore his men wexed all angry and wrothe &amp; forſothe he wolde gladly here the hermyte preche and made his men for to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke all nyght wherfore they wolde gladly haue hadde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hermyte deed. And ſo it be fell vpon a nyght y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met hadde well dronken wyne and fell a ſlepe / and his men toke his ſwerde oute of his ſhethe whyles that he laye and ſlepte ſo faſt &amp; ſlewe therwith this hermyte. And then they put vp his ſwerde agayne in his ſhethe all blody and vpon the morowe whan he founde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myte deed he was wrothe out of mefure and wolde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſtayne his men. But they with one accorde ſayde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hymſelfe hadde ſlayne hym whan he was dronken. And then they badde hym loke vpon his ſwerde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was all blody. And whan he behelde it he wende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had ſayde ſothe and this is the ſeconde myracle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Marchmet dyde / and he curſed the wyne and all them that dronkke
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny wyne. And therfore the ſaraſyns dare not drynke no wyne but ſome drynke it pryuely for and they drynke good beuerage and nouryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hynge the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is made of Camamyle and thereof is the ſugre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Alſo it be falleth ſomtyme that cryſten men be come ſaraſyns eyther thrughe pouerte or throughe wycked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and whan y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced the cryſten fayth they lerne hym theyr fals bylyue and maketh hym for to ſaye thus whan they receyue hym.</p>
            <p>¶ La oles ella Machamet roſes alla.</p>
            <p>¶ That is to ſaye / there is no god but one and Macha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>met is his meſſenger. &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21391:6"/>
            <p>Alſo the turkes byleue is ſtrongly kepte in theyr cyrcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyſyon. And they ben cyrcumcyſed whan they be of the aege of .xii. yere for Iſmael Abrahams fyrſt ſone was circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyſed at thyrten yere olde of whome they be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all proceded &amp; comen. And that lawe they kepe ſtyll after the olde maner / and theyr byleue is that they may dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke no wyne. And theyr lawe is that they ſholde praye &amp; faſte moche but they kepe it but lytell. But Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met knewe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our lorde Iheſu cryſt was god &amp; man And he ſayth alſo in his Alcaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes put not our lorde Iheſu cryſt vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe nor put hym not vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to deth. For the turkes ſaye that whan they wolde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue taken out lorde they toke Iudas his traytoure in his ſtede. For thy ſaye that our lorde Iheſu cryſt had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de altred hymſelfe in his lykeneſſe &amp; incontynent as he hadde done this he wente into heuen and Iudas was put vpon the cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe in his ſtede thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yr
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>als byle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e. And ſhall come again in the end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the worlde &amp; Iuge and ſhall dyſtroye
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tecryſt. And they ſaye that ſuche a grete ꝓphete wolde not deye ſuche a ſhame full dethe. For he dyde aray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the deed and in this fals opy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyon they accorde with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſecte of Manacheen &amp; they ſaye that the croſſe is a token of the deuyll and that no man ſholde worſhyp it. And they byleue not that he is aryſen from dethe vnto lyfe and they forſake. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of holy c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rche the whiche ben ronne out of his holy fyue wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche kepe vs frome all myſbyleue and brynge vs in to euerlaſtynge Ioye there as his holy ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>des ben bryghter &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayrer than the ſonne. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21391:7"/>
            <p>¶Thus endeth the Alcaron of the Turkes lawe / made by the fals Nygromancer Machamet. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prynted at London in Fleteſtrete in the ſygne of the Sonne by me Wynkyn de worde.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>wynkyn .de. worde.</head>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21391:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
